CHAPTER 5. a device from a Caterpillar The Caterpillar and Alice looked at each
other for some time in silence: at last the Caterpillar took the hookah
out of its mouth, and addressed her in a language sleepy voice.
“Who are you?
said the Caterpillar.
This was not an encouraging opening for a conversation.
Alice replied, rather shyly, “I— —I hardly know, sir, just at present— —at least I know
who I was when I got up this morning, but I think I must have been changed several
times since then.” “What do you mean by that?” said the Caterpillar sternly. “Explain yourself!”
“I can’t explain myself I’m afraid, sir,” said Alice, “because I’m not myself, you see.”
“I don’t see,” said the Caterpillar.
“I’m afraid I can’t put it more clearly,” Alice replied very politely, “for I can’t
understand it myself to begin with; and being so many different sizes in a day
is very confusing.” “It isn’t,” said the Caterpillar.
“Well, perhaps you haven’t found it so yet,” said Alice; “but when you have to turn
into a chrysalis— —you will someday you know— —and then after that into a
butterfly, I should think you’ll feel it a little queer, won’t you?” “Not a bit,”
said the Caterpillar.
“Well, perhaps your feelings may be different,” said Alice; “all I know is, it
would feel very queer to me “You!” said the Caterpillar contemptuously. “Who are you?
Which brought them back again to the beginning of the conversation. Alice felt
a little irritated at the caterpillars making such very short remarks, and she
drew herself up and said, very gravely, “I think, you ought to tell me who you are, first.”
“Why?” said the Caterpillar.
Here was another puzzling question; and as Alice could not think of any good
reason, and as the Caterpillar seemed to be in a very unpleasant state of mind,
she turned away. “Come back!” the Caterpillar called after her I have
something important to say!” This sounded promising, certainly:
Alice turned and came back again.
“Keep your temper,” said the Caterpillar.
“Is that all?” said Alice, swallowing down her anger as well as she could.
“No,” said the Caterpillar.
Alice thought she might as well wait, as she had nothing else to do, and perhaps
after all it might tell her something worth hearing.
For some minutes it puffed away without speaking, but at last it unfolded its
arms, took the hookah out of its mouth again, and said,
“So you think you’re changed, do you?”
“I’m afraid I am, sir,” said Alice; “I can’t
remember things as I used— —and I don’t keep the same size for 10 minutes together!”
“Can’t remember what things?” said the Caterpillar.
“Well, I’ve tried to say “How doth the little busy bee,” but it all came out
different!” Alice replied in a very melancholy voice. “Repeat, You are old,
Father William said the Caterpillar.
Alice folded her hands, and began:— “You are old, Father William,” the young man
said, “And your hair has become very white; And yet you incessantly stand on your
head— Do you think, at your age, it is right?” “In my youth,” Father William replied to
his son, “I feared it might injure the brain; But, now that I’m perfectly sure I
have none, Why, I do it again and again.” “You are old,” said the youth, “as I
mentioned before, And have grown most uncommonly fat; Yet you turned a back somersault in at
the door— Pray, what is the reason of that?”
“In my youths at the sage, as he shook his gray locks, “I kept all my limbs very
supple By the use of this ointment— —one shilling the box— Allow me to sell you a couple?”
“You are old,” said the youth, “and your jaws are too weak For anything tougher than
suet; Yet you finished the goose, with the bones and the beak— Pray, how did you
manage to do it?” “In my youths at his father, “I took to the law, And argued each
case with my wife; And the muscular strength, which it gave to my jaw, Has
lasted the rest of my life.” “You are old,” said the youth, “one would hardly suppose
That your eye was as steady as ever; Yet you balanced an eel on the end of your
nose— What made you so awfully clever?” “I have answered three questions, and that
is enough,” Said his father; “don’t give yourself heirs Do you think I can listen
all day to such stuff? Be off, or I’ll kick you downstairs
That has not said right,” said the Caterpillar.
“Not quite right, I’m afraid,” said Alice, timidly; “some of the words have got
altered.” “It is wrong from beginning to end,” said the Caterpillar decidedly, and
there was silence for some minutes.
The Caterpillar was the first to speak.
“What size do you want to be he said Oh, I’m not particular as to size,” Alice
hastily replied; “only one doesn’t like changing so often, you know.” “I don’t know,”
said the Caterpillar.
Alice said nothing she'd never been so much contradicted in her life before, and
she felt that she was losing her temper.
“Are you content now?” said the Caterpillar.
“Well, I should like to be a little larger, sir, if you wouldn’t mind,” said Alice:
“three inches is such a wretched height to be.” “It is a very good height indeed!” said the
Caterpillar angrily, rearing itself upright as it spoke (it was exactly three inches high).
“But I’m not used to it!” pleaded poor Alice in a piteous tone. And she thought
of herself, “I wish the creatures wouldn’t be so easily offended!”
“You’ll get used to it in time,” said the Caterpillar; and it put the hookah into
its mouth and began smoking again.
This time Alice waited patiently until it chose to speak again.
In a minute or two the Caterpillar took the hookah out of its mouth and yawned
once or twice, and shook itself.
Then it got down off the mushroom, and crawled away in the grass, merely remarking as it went,
“One side will make you grow taller, and the other side
will make you grow shorter.” “One side of what?
The other side of what? thought Alice to herself.
“Of the mushroom,” said the Caterpillar, just as if she had asked it aloud;
and in another moment it was out of sight.
Alice remained looking thoughtfully at the mushroom for a minute, trying to make
out which were the two sides of it; and as it was perfectly round, she found this
a very difficult question.
However, at last she stretched her arms around it as far as they would go, and
broke off a bit of the edge with each hand.
“And now which is which?” she said to herself, and nibbled a little of the
right hand bit to try the effect: the next moment she felt a violent blow
underneath her chin: it had struck her foot!
She was a good deal frightened by this very sudden change,
but she felt that there was no time to be lost and she was shrinking rapidly; so
she set to work at once to eat some of the other bit. Her chin was pressed so
closely against her foot, that there was hardly room to open her mouth; but she
did it at last, and managed to swallow a morsel of the left hand bit. “Come, my
hands free at last!” said Alice in a tone of delight, which
changed into alarm in another moment, when she found that her shoulders were
nowhere to be found: all she could see, when she looked down, was an immense
length of neck, which seemed to rise like a stalk out of a sea of green leaves
that lay far below her. “What can all that green stuff be?” said Alice. “And where have
my shoulders got to? And oh, my poor hands,
how is it I can’t see you?” She was moving
them about as she spoke, but no result seemed to follow, except a little shaking
among the distant green leaves.
As there seemed to be no chance of getting her hands up to her head, she
tried to get her head down to them, and was delighted to find that her neck
would bend about easily in any direction, like a serpent.
She had just succeeded in curving it down into a graceful zigzag, and was
going to dive in among the leaves, which she found to be nothing but the tops of
the trees under which she had been wandering, when a sharp hiss made her draw back in
a hurry: a large pigeon had flown into her face, and was beating her violently with its wings.
“Serpent!” screamed the Pigeon. “I’m not a serpent!” said Alice indignantly. “Let me alone
sir pentai say again!” repeated the Pigeon, but in a more subdued tone, and added
with a kind of saw I’ve tried every way, and nothing seems to suit them!”
“I haven’t the least idea what you’re talking about,” said Alice. “I’ve tried the
roots of trees, and I’ve tried banks, and I’ve tried hedges,” the Pigeon went on,
without attending to her; “but those serpents! There’s no pleasing them!” Alice
was more and more puzzled, but she thought there was no use in saying
anything more till the Pigeon had finished.
“As if it wasn’t trouble enough hatching the eggs,” said the Pigeon; “but I must be
on the lookout for serpents night and day! Why, I haven’t had a wink of sleep
these three weeks!” “I’m very sorry you’ve been annoyed,” said
Alice, who is beginning to see its meaning. “And just as I had taken the
highest tree in the wood,” continued the Pigeon, raising its voice to a shriek,
“and just as I was thinking I would be free of them at last, they must needs
come wriggling down from the sky oh Serpent!” “But I’m not a serpent, I tell you!”
said Alice. “I’m a— —I’m a—” “Well! What are you
cried the Pigeon. “I can see you’re trying to invent something!” “I— —I’m a little girl,”
said Alice, rather doubtfully, as she remembered the number of changes she had
gone through that day.
“A likely story indeed!” said the Pigeon in a tone of deepest contempt. “I’ve seen a
good many little girls in my time, but never one with such a neck as that! No, no!
You’re a serpent; and there’s no use to denying it. I suppose you’ll be telling
me next that you've never tasted an egg!” “I have tasted eggs, certainly,” said Alice,
who was a very truthful child; “but little girls eat eggs quite as much as serpents
do, you know.” “I don’t believe it,” said the Pigeon;
“but if they do, why then they are kind of a serpent, that’s all I can say.”
This was such a new idea to Alice, that she was quite silent for a minute or two,
which gave the Pigeon the opportunity of adding or looking for eggs, I know that
well enough; and what does it matter to me whether you’re a little girl or a
serpent?” “It matters a good deal to me said Alice hastily; “but I’m not looking
for eggs, as it happens; and if I was, I
shouldn’t want yours I don’t like them raw.” “Well, be off, then!”
said the Pigeon in a sulky tone, as it settled down again into its nest. Alice
crouched down among the trees as well as she could, for her neck kept getting
entangled among the branches, and every now and then she had to stop and untwist
it. After a while she remembered that she still held the piece of mushroom in her
hands, and she set to work very carefully, nibbling first at one and then at the
other, and growing sometimes taller and sometimes shorter, until she had
succeeded in bringing herself down to her usual height. It was so long since
she had been anything near the right size, that it felt quite strange at first;
but she got used to it in a few minutes, and began talking to herself, as usual.
“Come, there’s half my plan done now! How puzzling all these changes are! I’m never
sure what I’m going to be, from one minute to another! However, I’ve got back
to my right size: the next thing is, to get into that beautiful garden—
—how is that to be done, I wonder?” As she said this, she came suddenly upon
an open place, with a little house in it about four feet high.
“Whoever lives there,” thought Alice, “it’ll never do to come upon them this size:
why, I should frighten them out of their wits!” So she began nibbling at the
right-hand bit again, and did not venture to go near the house until she had
brought herself down to nine inches high